Ashish Panigrahi

• https://ashishpanigrahi.me

■ ashish.panigrahi@niser.ac.in • paniash • in ashish-panigrahi99

About me

I am a 3^{rd} year physics student studying at the **National Institute of Science Education and Research, Bhubaneswar, India**. I am interested in quantum physics & quantum computing with its application in the field of science and technology.

Nationality: Indian

Education

• National Institute of Science Education and Research Integrated Master's (CGPA till 4th semester: 9.30/10.0) Bhubaneswar, India 2018 - 2023

- Major in physics with a minor in computer science.
- Relevant coursework:
 - * Physics:
 - · Theory Quantum mechanics, Classical mechanics, Statistical mechanics, Electromagnetism, Special Theory of relativity, Nuclear & particle physics.
 - · Labs Computational Lab, Electronics Lab, Modern Physics Lab.
 - * Mathematics: Mathematical methods, Set Theory, Real Analysis.
 - * Computer Science: Theory of Computation, Discrete Structures (Combinatorics & Graph theory), Design and Analysis of Algorithms, Programming & Data structures lab.
- Maharishi Vidya Mandir Senior Sec. School

Chennai, India

All India Senior Secondary Certificate Examination (CBSE) - 95.6%

May 2018

- Subjects taken: Physics, Mathematics, Chemistry, Computer Science, English.
- Received a perfect score in Computer Science (Object Oriented Programming in C++).
- PSG Public School

Coimbatore, India

All India Secondary School Examination (CBSE) - CGPA 10

May 2016

- Subjects taken: Science, Mathematics, Social Sciences, English, Hindi.

Honors/Awards

• National Graduate Physics Examination (National topper) Indian Association of Physics Teachers 2020

- Secured a score among the top 118 students in the country.

• Department Topper $(1^{st} \& 2^{nd} \ year)$

2018-2020

• Kishore Vaigyanik Protsahan Yojana

2017

Indian Institute of Science

Bengaluru, India

 A prestigious fellowship program funded by the Department of Science and Technology of the Government of India.

• National Talent Search Examination

2016

National Council of Education Research and Training

New Delhi, India

- A national level scholarship program offered by the Government of India.
- It is one of the oldest and most prestigious scholarship programmes in the country.

Academic exposure

• Quantum Winter Hackathon

Virtual

BosonQ Psi, Quantum Computing India

December 2020

- A month long hackathon involving the discretization of 1D wave equation using implicit time integration scheme. Also showed the speedup between classical approach and quantum implementation using HHL algorithm.
- Scored among the top 10 teams around the world.

IBM Quantum Challenge (Fall) IBM

Virtual

November 2020

 A 3 week competition which involved solving puzzles of varying difficulty level using Grover's algorithm and implemented using Qiskit.

• Global Quantum Programming Workshop QWorld

Virtual

November 2020

- A 5-day workshop introducing the basics of quantum computing, with hands-on coding exercises using Qiskit.
- Cleared the quizzes and received a diploma for the same.

• Qiskit India Challenge

Virtual

IBM Quantum

September 2020

- A 2 week hackathon which involved the basics of programming quantum circuits using Qiskit.
- The final challenge involved the implementation of a variational quantum classifier (VQC) to separate the digits '4' and '9' from an MNIST dataset through machine learning. My team achieved an overall model accuracy of 79.6%.

• Mini School on quantum machine learning

South Africa

National Institute for Theoretical Physics

September 2020

- A 4 week summer school involving lectures by Amira Mahomed Abbas on the fundamentals of quantum machine learning through Qiskit and PennyLane.
- Scored above 90% in the 2 quizzes held during the school to qualify for a certificate.

• Qiskit Global Summer School

Virtual

IBM Quantum

July-August 2020

- An intensive 2 week virtual summer school on quantum computation and designing quantum circuits and algorithms using Qiskit.
- Did hands-on coding exercises to learn various quantum algorithms, pulse level control of qubits and concepts in quantum chemistry.
- Also did a project on simulating the ground energy level of LiH molecule using quantum variational eigensolver.

• National Initiative on Undergraduate Science (Physics) Homi Bhabha Centre for Science Education, TIFR

Mumbai, Maharashtra

June 2019

- Selected as one of top 70 students in the country to participate in this camp.
- An extensive 12-day course containing lectures, independent lab work and a field trip for 2 days.
- Lecture series on quantum mechanics, quantum information theory and quantum computation, basic condensed matter physics, many body physics, astronomy and astrophysics.
- About 30 hours of independent lab work.
- Field trip to Giant Meterwave Radio Telescope (GMRT) and National Centre for Radio Astrophysics (NCRA).

• National Science (VIJYOSHI) Camp

Bengaluru, Karnataka

Indian Institute of Science

December 2018

 3 day science camp organized by the *Institute of Science* and constituting of lecture series on scientific research.

Academic experience

• Classification of quantum correlations and channels Bose.X (bosex.org)

Remote

December 2020 - Present

- Working on understanding induced quantum correlations under noisy environments and classification schemes with its application in quantum optics.
- Software used: PIQS, QuTiP

• Summer Project on Anisotropic Magnetoresistance Institute of Physics, Bhubaneswar

Bhubaneswar, India May - June 2019

- Project guide: Dr. Debakanta Samal, Reader-F, Institute of Physics

 Topics covered: Origin of magnetoresistance, theory of magnetoresistance in real metals using the 2-band charge carrier model, origin of anisotropic magnetoresistance, its applications and current research scenario in the field.

Open-source contributions

• Qiskit Textbook

GitHub

Learn Quantum Computation using Qiskit

April 2020 - Present

- Qiskit is IBM's software development kit for building software to interact with IBM's quantum devices and OpenQASM.
- The textbook is equivalent to a university level course for learning quantum computation and beyond.
- I have been an active contributor to this project with over 30+ commits since April 2020.

Licenses & Certifications

• Certificate of Recognition Boson Q Psi, QCI, ISCFD BosonQ Psi

December 2020

- In recognition of exemplary performance at "Quantum Winter Hackathon 2020".
- Scored among the top 10 teams from around the world.

• Challenge Fall 2020 Achievement - Intermediate

IBM

IBM Quantum

December 2020

- Demonstrated an ability to implement near-future quantum data structures and design a quantum game solver using Grover's algorithm.
- Showed an understanding of quantum circuits, the gates that comprise such circuits, Grover's algorithm, and qRAM (quantum random access memory) as a way to implement complex data structures.

• Certificate of Quantum Proficiency

 $_{\rm IBM}$

IBM Quantum

September 2020

- For demonstrating an applied understanding of the basics of Quantum Computing using Qiskit, plus the ability to apply and experiment with classical machine learning techniques and the *Variational Quantum Classifier* (VQC) algorithm.
- CS-191x: Quantum Mechanics and Quantum Computation

 edX

University of California, Berkeley

August 2020

- Coursework involved ranging from the basics of the qubit to quantum algorithms such as Grover's, Shor's etc. to the Bloch sphere and Schrödinger's wave equation.
- Final score: 97%

• Certificate of Quantum Excellence

 $_{\rm IBM}$

IBM Quantum

July 2020

 Received for demonstrating applied understanding and comfort with and about Quantum Computing using Qiskit.

Volunteering

I have worked under the **Avanti Fellows** NGO programme during the months January-April 2019 as a mentor. My weekend work involved having a one-to-one discussion with students of classes XI and XII of **Jawahar Navodaya Vidyalaya** (JNV) **Dhenkanal**, **Odisha**, **India**.

Technical skills

Programming and scripting languages

C, C++, Shell scripting, R and Python (Libraries: Scipy, Numpy, Matplotlib, Sympy)

Markup languages

LATEX, Markdown, Groff, HTML

Quantum Frameworks

Qiskit, PennyLane, QuTiP

General computing literacy

Proficient in operating GNU/Linux (includes Debian and Arch Linux derivatives) & Windows, terminal commands, **tmux** multiplexer, gnuplot and **Vim** text editor. I also have a working knowledge of **Git**, a version control system.

